<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<chapter id="changes">
    <title>New and Noteworthy</title>
    <section id="v0.5">
        <title>v0.5</title>
        <subtitle>Planned for 2012-02-XX, first official release. Formal review needs to be scheduled.</subtitle>
        <section>
            <title>Bugzilla Summaries</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        List of
                        <ulink url="http://goo.gl/g96bt">closed bugs</ulink>
                        for v0.5.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        List of
                        <ulink url="http://goo.gl/7JfIM">open bugs</ulink>
                        for v0.5.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        List of
                        <ulink url="http://goo.gl/8QG32">all plan items</ulink>
                        for v1.0.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>New Feature Namespaces</title>
            <simpara>
                We outgrew our initial naming scheme. For v0.5 we changed the namespace of our features and plug-ins
                completely. As result, using the update manager wont work as expected. You have to uninstall previous
                versions and install code recommenders from one of our
                <ulink url="http://eclipse.org/recommenders/download/">update sites</ulink>
                .
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Removal of Project Builder and Nature</title>
            <para>
                Earlier version of Code Recommenders required to
                <emphasis>activate</emphasis>
                Recommenders on a per-project basis. This activation added a
                <emphasis>builder</emphasis>
                to the project that analyzed file changes whenever Eclipse decided to run the builders (on save or on
                workspace fresh etc.) and stored the analysis results in a
                <filename>.recommenders/</filename>
                folder. With v0.5 this is not required anymore. Code Recommenders now analyzes the compilation unit
                on-the-fly whenever code completion is triggered. Developers now can easily use Code Recommenders
                without changing any project configuration file. Just install-and-go.
            </para>
            <important>
                <simpara> Please note that currently only Eclipse APIs like JFace, SWT, Workbench etc. are supported.
                    Adding support for other frameworks is planned for v0.6 and v0.7.
                </simpara>
            </important>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Completion Engines completely based on JDT</title>
            <para>
                Related to the previous change, we also switched from the
                <ulink url="http://wala.sf.net">WALA bytecode analysis toolkit</ulink>
                to
                <emphasis>Eclipse JDT</emphasis>
                as primary analysis tool for code completion. WALA will, however, still be the analysis toolkit of
                choice for sophisticated code analysis and data exports. There is yet no better analysis toolkit
                available that suites our needs.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>JDT-based Call Chain Completion</title>
            <para>
                With v0.5, Code Recommenders ships a new version of its
                <ulink url="http://eclipse.org/recommenders/documentation/completion/">chain completion engine</ulink>
                completely based on JDT. Thanks to Marko Martin who
                <ulink url="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=359694">contributed this</ulink>
                to Code Recommenders. Since this code is a major rewrite of the existing engine, please
                <ulink url="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/enter_bug.cgi?product=Recommenders">report any issues</ulink>
                you experience to bugzilla.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Extended Documentation Platform</title>
            <para>
                Based on Stefan Henss' work in this year's
                <ulink url="http://stefanhenss.com/summing-up-eclipse-extdoc">Google Summer of Code</ulink>
                project, this release ships with an updated version of Stefan's
                <emphasis>Extdoc View</emphasis>
                . Internally, we changed the code to be easily extensible by other contributors. Check
                <link linkend="isv-extdoc"> Extended Documentation Platform ISV documentation
                </link>
                for more details on that.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Improved Subwords Completion</title>
            <para>
                For assignments,
                <emphasis>subwords completion</emphasis>
                now takes into account the variable name of the assignment.
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.5/subwords-assignment.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                The exact implementation of the matching and ranking strategy is subject to change. If you have ideas on
                how to improve the current strategy, look at the
                <ulink
                    url="http://git.eclipse.org/c/recommenders/org.eclipse.recommenders.git/tree/plugins/org.eclipse.recommenders.completion.rcp.subwords2/src/org/eclipse/recommenders/internal/completion/rcp/subwords2/AssignmentVarnameMatchCompletionProposalComputer.java">code</ulink>
                and send your ideas to the
                <ulink url="http://eclipse.org/forums/eclipse.recommenders">forum</ulink>
                .
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Temporary Deactivation of Template Completion</title>
            <para>
                In v0.2 we added a new
                <link linkend="changes-v0.2-templates">template completion engine</link>
                to Code Recommenders. Due to the large internal refactorings, this engine was left out of this release
                but will be added again in v0.6.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Forecast: New Local Code-search</title>
            <para>
                Yet, Code Recommenders ships without official code search support. However, there is some work going on
                in this area. Previous updates offered first draft of code-search client in the
                <emphasis>experimental</emphasis>
                section of the update site. For v0.5 we removed this feature from the update sites as it's currently
                developed by Tobias Boehm, a Student at Darmstadt University of Technology as part of his Master thesis.
                For the curious, the sources can be found in
                <ulink
                    url="http://code.google.com/a/eclipselabs.org/p/code-recommenders/source/browse/?repo=codesearch-tobias">Code Recommenders' Labs repository</ulink>
                . If you are interested in bleeding edge state of (local) code-search, there is also an
                <ulink
                    url="http://vandyk.st.informatik.tu-darmstadt.de/updates/students/ep/codesearch-tobias/repositories/org.eclipselabs.recommenders.repository.codesearchquery/target/repository/">temporary update site</ulink>
                . Please send your questions regarding local code-search to the
                <ulink url="http://eclipse.org/forums/eclipse.recommenders">forum</ulink>
                .
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="v0.4">
        <title>v0.4</title>
        <subtitle>Published on 2011-11-07</subtitle>
        <section>
            <title>Maintenance Release</title>
            <para>This is a maintenance release without any new features.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="v0.3">
        <title>v0.3</title>
        <subtitle>Published on 2011-08-26</subtitle>
        <section>
            <title>Subwords Completion</title>
            <para>Sometimes you just don't know the complete name of a method - or entering its full name from the first
                character? Subwords is here to assist.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on method calls:</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.3/subwords-completion-on-method-calls.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on variables:</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.3/subwords-completion-on-variables.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on method overrides:</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.3/subwords-completion-on-method-overrides.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
        </section>
        <para>
            Subwords has been mainly developed by Paul-Emmanuel Faidherbe and contributed to Eclipse Code Recommenders.
            Thank you Paul-Emmanuel!
            <note>
                <title>Subwords currently has some limitations:</title>
                <para> It doesn't support dynamic reranking of proposals with better/larger overlaps. It only works in
                    the scenarios shown above. Typename completions are yet not possible. You may find more limitations
                    as you go. Please send your feature requests and bugs to Bugzilla. A thread discussing this
                    contribution is here: https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=350000
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="v0.2">
        <title>v0.2</title>
        <subtitle>Published on 2011-03-01</subtitle>
        <section>
            <title>Chain Completion</title>
            <para>
                How many times did you ask yourself
                <emphasis>"How do I get an instance of X?"</emphasis>
                And how much time did you spent with shimming from one method call to another to find a call chain
                returning the type you were looking for?
            </para>
            <para> Clearly, by far too long. Code Recommenders' new chain completion engine supports you in finding all
                applicable call chains and thus saves you lots of time when learning new APIs. How does it work? In a
                nutshell, Code Recommenders takes the current context code completion was triggered in and starts a
                search on all local variables, fields and methods of the enclosing class recursively until a path to the
                requested type is found (or a time out occurred :D). If it could find some valid paths, it generates
                ready-to-use code snippets the developer can immediately insert into her code. Look at the screenshots
                below for some examples:
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>
                    Completion on
                    <code>this</code>
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.2/chain-completion-on-IStatusLineManager.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on static types
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.2/chain-completion-on-platformui.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on method returns
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.2/chain-completion-on-method-return.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion with type cast
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.2/chain-completion-with-cast.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="changes-v0.2-templates">
            <title>Templates Completion Engine</title>
            <para> Have you ever wondered how to deal with a new framework's objects? Or got tired by continuously
                writing the same procedures, e.g. instantiating an object and calling a bunch of setters!? For this
                Eclipse contains standard-templates but they are only few and writing new is time-consuming and often
                difficult to do.
            </para>
            <para> Our templates completion engine provides templates dynamically created on completion requests. They
                are not manually crafted but obtained from frequent patterns found in real-life framework usage, i.e.
                you are instantly served with the most common practices. For this not only the object type is
                considered, but also what has already been done with the variable itself - our templates are
                context-sensitive! You can see how they adopt to different occasion in the following screenshots. With
                this the new templates completion engine provides valuable dynamic shortcuts for frequent code blocks
                and is also able to guide framework novices with relevant examples.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Completion for Local Declaration
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.2/template-completion-on-button-declaration.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Dynamic Pattern Completion
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.2/template-completion-on-button-with-observed-calls.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="v0.1">
        <title>v0.1</title>
        <subtitle>Published on 2011-02-15</subtitle>
        <section>
            <title>Calls Completion</title>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on Declared Variables</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.1/completion-on-field.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on This</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.1/completion-on-this.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on Anonymous Method Returns</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.1/completion-on-method-return.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Completion from Anonymous Inner Classes</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.1/completion-on-local-from-nested.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>On-the-fly Code Analysis</title>
                <para> Code Recommenders performs several static analyses on your code whenever you save your editor
                    contents. However, sometimes you work a while with a dirty editor (i.e., editor contains un-safed
                    changes). If code completion now was triggered on variables added after the last save code
                    recommenders couldn't make any recommendations for these variables. This update now contains an
                    on-the-fly analyzer that performs a flat analysis of your current method body whenever code
                    completion is triggered on a previously unknown variable based on the information it obtains from
                    the JDT AST.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Performance Improvements</title>
                <para> Code Completion's performance has been improve quite a lot. However, the loading of recommender
                    models may take a second and thus may slow down your code completion on the first load. After the
                    models are loaded, code completion usually takes between 10 to 50 ms.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Overrides Completion</title>
            <section>
                <title>Completion on Class Body</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.1/completion-on-class-body.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Eclipse Help
            </title>
            <para> Code Recommenders follows the model of EGit and Mylyn and maintains its user and developer guides as
                well as its new and noteworthy release notes in wiki.eclipse.org. This allows developers and users
                likewise to edit and comment on existing documentation. The latest version of these wiki pages are
                automatically integrated into the latest Eclipse Help plug-in and changes are available immediately to
                you.
            </para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/figures/changes/v0.1/eclipse-help-user.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>